{"tossups": [{"question": "News of this event was first reported by Jeff Gerth of the <em>New York Times</em>. A year later, documents pertaining to this event were removed by Bernard Nussbaum [[NUSS-bowm]] and given to Maggie Williams to place in a safe on the third floor of the White House. The first public investigation into this event was conducted by Kenneth Starr, who broadened the investigation to include the Monica Lewinsky affair. For the point, name this political controversy involving Arkansas real estate investments by Bill Clinton.", "answer": "<b><u>Whitewater</u></b> controversy (or <b><u>Whitewater</u></b> scandal)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A ruler of this family formally surrendered and abdicated to a joint UK-USSR invasion of his nation in Operation Countenance. The formal deposition of the last ruler of the Qajar [[kah-JAR]] family while abroad on a European tour led to the appointment of this dynasty's first ruler. A member of this dynasty created a one-party state in the mid 1970s under the Rastakhiz [[rah-STAH-\"keys\"]] party, part of a reform package known as the \"White Revolution.\" The Islamic Revolution overthrew, for the point, which dynasty of Persian shahs in the 20th century?", "answer": "<b><u>Pahlavi</u></b> Dynasty", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This artist drew from Jerry Grandenetti's war-themed \"Wingmate of Doom\" for his own painting titled <em>As I Opened Fire</em>. This artist depicted \"a scarred German submarine captain at a battle station\" in his 1963 painting <em>Torpedo...Los!</em>. The title of one of this artist\u2019s paintings is displayed in bold yellow text in front of an exploding fighter jet, which took inspiration from his time fighting in World War Two. For the point, name this Pop artist whose comic book style is seen in works like <em>Whaam!</em>.", "answer": "Roy <b><u>Lichtenstein</u></b> (or Roy Fox <b><u>Lichtenstein</u></b>)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "David III Bagrat reinforced a rebellion against this man's rule perpetrated by the general Bardas Phokas [[FOH-kas]]. This \"purple-born\" emperor likely had his co-ruler, John, poisoned upon his return from a campaign against the Abbasids. The conversion of the Rus occurred after this man offered his sister, Anna, in marriage to Vladimir the Great. The blinding of the majority of Tsar Samuel's army led to, for the point, which Byzantine emperor earning the epithet \"Bulgar-slayer?\"", "answer": "<b><u>Basil</u></b> the Bulgar Slayer (or <b><u>Basil</u></b>eios ho Boulgaroktonos; accept <b><u>Basil</u></b> II Porphyrogenitus; or <b><u>Basil</u></b>eios Porphyrogenn\u0113tos; accept <b><u>Basil</u></b>, Born in the Purple before \"purple-born\")", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "In this decade, Irene Langhorne served as the model for the so-called \"Gibson Girl\" and due to the sudden widespread availability of a certain dye, this period is sometimes called the \"Mauve Decade.\" Wage cuts and failure to lower local rent led to the Pullman Strike in this decade. William Jennings Bryan gave the \"Cross of Gold\" speech in this decade, and the U.S. Seventh Cavalry committed the Wounded Knee Massacre at its beginning. The Spanish-American War occurred during, for the point, which decade of the late 19th century?", "answer": "<b><u>1890</u></b>s (accept the <b><u>Gay Nineties</u></b>; prompt on \"the Nineties\"; prompt on \"Mauve Decade\" before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Albert the Bear served as margrave of this state, then known as the Northern March, after successfully crusading against the Wendish people in the 12th century. A World War Two-era \"Conference\" named for this state's capital involved Harry Truman, Clement Atlee and Joseph Stalin planning how to administer occupied Germany. Frederick III united a joint realm between this state and Prussia into a kingdom. The state of Berlin is entirely surrounded by, for the point, what formerly-Soviet occupied German state governed from Potsdam?", "answer": "<b><u>Brandenburg</u></b> (accept <b><u>Brannenborg</u></b>; or <b><u>Bramborska</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Following a loss to Napoleon, a large contingent of this group was granted residency in Russia by Emperor Paul I, while others from this group rejected a Swedish offer of sovereignty over Gotland. After the fall of the County of Tripoli, this group moved to Rhodes, before an Ottoman invasion forced them to relocate to Malta, where they won the last major victory for a group of knights in 1565. For the point, name this order of knights whose name derives from their role as guardians of a medical center for Christian pilgrims in Jerusalem.", "answer": "Knights <b><u>Hospital</u></b>ler (accept Order of Knights of the <b><u>Hospital</u></b> of Saint John of Jerusalem; or Knights of <b><u>St. John</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "The Plattsburg Movement taught certain skills in anticipation of this policy decision, which was also the subject of the Preparedness Movement. Public relations efforts in favor of this decision were managed by the Creel Committee. This large policy decision was defended in public speeches by the Four Minute Men, who also solicited Liberty Loans. The publication of the Zimmermann Telegram and lingering anger over the sinking of the <em>Lusitania</em> led to, for the point, what 1917 decision to join a European conflict?", "answer": "The <b><u>United States entering World War One</u></b> (accept answers referring to the decision of the <b><u>United States</u></b> or <b><u>U.S.A.</u></b> to enter, join, participate, fight, etc. in <b><u>World War</u></b> <b><u>One</u></b> or the <b><u>First World War</u></b> or the <b><u>Great War</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This leader tried to ease tensions by granting money to Maynooth College. This leader\u2019s subordinate Richard Pakenham negotiated the Oregon boundary dispute. Daniel O\u2019Connell challenged this leader to a duel for opposing Catholic emancipation. This leader wrote the Tamworth Manifesto, forming the principles of the Conservative Party, and repealed the Corn Laws in the wake of the Irish Potato Famine. For the point, name this prime minister who created London\u2019s Metropolitan Police Force.", "answer": "Robert <b><u>Peel</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "After learning about this conflict, Eoin [[\"Owen\"]] MacNeill placed a last-minute newscast advising people not to join the Cumann na mBan [[na MON]] and James Connolly\u2019s citizen army in this conflict. Following Patrick Pearse\u2019s surrender to General Lowe to end this conflict, sixteen rebel leaders were executed. This uprising saw the occupation of the General Post Office and declaration of a republic. For the point, name this armed insurrection of Irish republicans that took place during an eponymous week.", "answer": "<b><u>Easter Rising</u></b> (or <b><u>Easter Rebellion</u></b>; accept <b><u>\u00c9ir\u00ed Amach na C\u00e1sca</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "With Shah Narseh, this ruler signed the Peace of Nisibis, giving his empire suzerainty over the kingdom of Iberia in the Caucasus. This ruler ordered the ineffective \"Edict on the Maximum Prices\" following a series of currency debasements during the Crisis of the Third Century. With his co-ruler, Maximian, this man ordered a massacre of the \"20,000 Martyrs of Nicomedia,\" part of larger set of Christian persecutions named for this emperor. For the point, name this Roman emperor of Greek descent who established the Tetrarchy.", "answer": "<b><u>Diocletian</u></b> (or Gaius Aurelius Valerius <b><u>Diocletian</u></b>us; accept <b><u>Diocles</u></b> Valerius; accept <b><u>Diocletian</u></b>ic Persecution)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "A notable catechism that came out of this event was developed primarily by Carlo Borromeo. This council authorized Paul III to begin developing what would become the Gregorian Calendar. This council officially reaffirmed the traditional books of the Bible and developed a namesake mass that would be in use for the next four hundred years. Denouncing the concept of \"justification by faith alone,\" for the point, what Church council condemned the teachings of Martin Luther and began the Counter-Reformation?", "answer": "Council of <b><u>Trent</u></b> (or Concilium <b><u>Tridentinum</u></b>; accept Catechism of the Council of <b><u>Trent</u></b>; or <b><u>Tridentine</u></b> Catechism; accept <b><u>Tridentine</u></b> Mass; accept <b><u>Tridentine</u></b> Creed)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "King Genseric strategically married his son to the daughter of king of these people, but later had her ears and nose mutilated for plotting against the Vandal prince, resulting in the siege of Barcelona. A king of these people, Reccared I, abandoned orthodox Christianity for Arianism as the state faith. A king of this people, Theodoric I, was instrumental in assisting Flavius Aetius's [[AY-shus-es]] victory over the Huns at the Battle of the Catalaunian Plains. The 410 sack of Rome was perpetrated by, for the point, which Gothic people under King Alaric I?", "answer": "<b><u>Visigoth</u></b>s (prompt on \"Goths\" alone\"; do not accept \"Ostrogoths\")", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "This city's Mamelles hills are the site of the African Renaissance Monument, while the village of Mbodiene outside this capital city will be the site of a Wakanda-inspired development named for the singer Akon. Leopold Sedar Senghor airport serves this city, where the House of Slaves on Gor\u00e9e Island now memorializes the Atlantic Slave trade. Originally founded by the Portuguese near the Cap-Vert peninsula, for the point, what Wolof and French-speaking city is the capital of Senegal?", "answer": "<b><u>Dakar</u></b> (or <b><u>Ndakaaru</u></b>)", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "Jeb Bush gave a sword once owned by this man to Marco Rubio, in reference to a Bush family joke about \"unleashing\" this man. After this man's regime was targeted in the February 28 Incident, he launched a \"White Terror\" against dissidents. This man was kidnapped along with his top generals in the 1936 Xi'an [[SHEE-ahn]] Incident in order to force him to ally with the Communists against Japan. For the point, name this leader of the Kuomintang [[gwoh-min-DONG]] who lost the Chinese Civil War and headed the government of Taiwan until his 1975 death.", "answer": "<b><u>Chiang</u></b> Kai-shek (or <b><u>Chiang</u></b> Chieh-shih; or <b><u>Chiang</u></b> Chung-cheng; or <b><u>Jiang</u></b> Jieshi)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Archaeologists found that 90% of bodies at the 1320s Crow Creek Massacre showed evidence of this practice. Henry Hamilton acquired a derogatory nickname from Continental Army soldiers for encouraging this practice. French and British commanders in the early 18th century encouraged this practice by paying $60 bounties for its product as proof of events such as the Battle of Pequawket against the Abenaki. For the point, name this practice, common in conflicts between or against American Indians, of removing skin from the head of a dead enemy.", "answer": "<b><u>Scalp</u></b>ing", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "For the last three decades of the 20th century, this country was governed by a \"New Order\" that collapsed following the Asian Financial Crisis and sweeping anti-Chinese riots. B.J. Habibie led the \"Reform Era\" of this nation, which attempted to liberalize the regime following the resignation of Suharto. This nation gained independence under Sukarno following the Japanese occupation of the East Indies. For the point, name this Asian nation whose Dutch capital, Batavia, was renamed Jakarta.", "answer": "Republic of <b><u>Indonesia</u></b> (accept Republik <b><u>Indonesia</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "A \"project\" named for this historical figure in Detroit led to 1942 riots between white homeowners from Conant Gardens who wished to stop the expansion of Black housing in the inner city. In commemoration of the deployment of the 1st Michigan Coloured Regiment, this figure wrote \"the Valiant Soldiers.\" This former slave said, \"I...can do as much work as any man\" in an oration given at a women's convention in Ohio. The \"Ain't I a Woman\" speech was given by, for the point, which Black and Women's rights activist of the mid-19th century?", "answer": "Sojourner <b><u>Truth</u></b> (accept Isabella <b><u>Baumfree</u></b>; accept the Sojourner <b><u>Truth</u></b> Project)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "After this man's 1964 arrest, he was slapped by the prime minister of his country, Hasan Ali Mansur, for refusing to cease his criticism of the government while working as a seminary teacher. In his first months in power, this man confronted political opposition by stating, \"I shall kick their teeth in. I appoint the government.\" That followed fourteen years of exile for this man, including time in cities like Najaf and Paris. For the point, name this leader of the Islamic Revolution of 1979, the first Supreme Leader of Iran.", "answer": "Ayatollah <b><u>Khomeini</u></b> (or Ruholla <b><u>Khomeini</u></b>; accept Sayyid Ruhollah Musavi <b><u>Khomeini</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "In this nation, the anti-immigrant rhetoric of politician Pim Fortuyn [[for-TOYN]] led to his assassination during its 2002 general election. A ban on all public mosques and printings of the Koran were called for by this nation's far right faction, the Party for Freedom. On the holiday of Koningsdag [[KOH-nings-dahk]] in 2013, the reigning Queen Beatrix abdicated in favor of her son Willem-Alexander, the head of the House of Orange-Nassau. Mark Rutte [[ROO-teh]] leads, for the point, which Benelux nation governed from The Hague?", "answer": "<b><u>Netherlands</u></b> (accept <b><u>Nederland</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "One of the oldest of these edifices in Maruoka [[[[mah-ROO-oh-KAH]] was subject to <em>hitobashira</em>, or human sacrifices by its foundation. Intentionally built a day's march apart, a network of these buildings existed between Busan and Seoul during the Chongyu War. The outbreak of the \u014cnin War between competing <em>daimyos</em> accelerated the pace of construction of these military buildings. <em>Shiro</em> is the Japanese word for, for the point, what type of stone fortress also common in Medieval Europe?", "answer": "Japanese <b><u>castle</u></b>s (accept <em><b><u>Shiro</u></b></em> or <b><u>Fortress</u></b>es before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "A scandal surrounding this industry began when Hugh Allan gave the Conservative party 360,000 dollars in exchange for a contract. It isn\u2019t gold mining, but hundreds of Chinese-Canadians died in nitroglycerin accidents while working on a project in this industry. That project in this industry was completed in Craigellachie [[kruh-GEH-luh-kee]] by Donald Smith. Cornelius Van Horne was a tycoon in, for the point, what industry that built the Canadian Pacific from Ontario to British Columbia?", "answer": "<b><u>Railway</u></b> Industry (accept the Canadian Pacific <b><u>Railway</u></b> before mentioned; accept synonyms for \"railway\" such as \"trains,\" \"rail,\" or \"railroads\")", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "On the DR 284 stone at the Hunnestad Monument, Ole Worm observed an image of one of these creatures holding two snakes and riding a wolf. That image is usually identified as Hyrrokin, a female example of these creatures who assisted in the funeral of Baldr. Another of these creatures, Utgard-Loki, challenged Thor to lift a cat and drink from a cup. The trickster god, Loki, was the son of one of these creatures, some of whom were believed to live in a realm of frost. For the point, name these creatures attested to in Norse poems.", "answer": "(Frost) <b><u>Giant</u></b>s (accept <b><u>J\u01ebtunn</u></b>; or <b><u>J\u00f6tnar</u></b>; accept Fire <b><u>Giants</u></b>)", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}, {"question": "The first of these institutions in the U.S. was founded by a man who won a gold medal at the Exposition Universelle for producing a malleable nickel that improved coinage. Republican Party co-founder, Amos Tuck, names an institution of this type at Dartmouth. A Pennsylvania institution of this type was created in 1881 by the co-founder of Bethlehem Steel, Joseph Wharton. The GMAT is the entrance exam for these schools, one of which was where Warren Buffett received an MBA. For the point, name these institutions where one can learn the principles of management and entrepreneurship.", "answer": "<b><u>Business school</u></b>s (prompt on \u201cgraduate schools\u201d or \u201cmanagement schools\u201d; prompt on \"college\" or \"University\"; prompt on partial answers)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A ruling against this state's replevin law, passed in response to the Panic of 1819, led to the establishment of a competing appellate system that existed for seven years. This location of the Old Court/New Court controversy was where Jereboam Beauchamp murdered Solomon Sharp in this state's namesake \"tragedy.\" Richard Mentor Johnson and John Breckenridge represented this state in the Senate. For the point, name this first slave state added after the original thirteen colonies, which sent Henry Clay to Congress in seven separate stints.", "answer": "<b><u>Kentucky</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This politician, who paid off George Floyd's daughter's college tuition, received an endorsement from a man who'd previously endorsed Andrew Yang. Elon Musk endorsed this politician, who alleged that the Democratic Party was intentionally giving the Black community the birth control \"Plan B\" to suppress their votes. This politician, who ran alongside Wyoming preacher Michelle Tidball, represented the \"Birthday Party.\" For the point, name this 2020 Presidential candidate and rapper whose campaign advisors included his then wife, Kim Kardashian.", "answer": "<b><u>Kanye</u><u>West</u></b> (accept either; accept <b><u>Yeezy</u></b>; prompt on \"Ye\")", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "Work done directly for this series of missions led to the invention of \"Development Before the Fact\" programming and the Universal Systems Language. Electrical engineer Judith Love Cohen contributed to these missions while giving birth. Margaret Hamilton's MIT Instrumentation Laboratory created the key software for these missions, whose ill-fated 1970 entry's emergency return path was calculated by Katherine Johnson. For the point, name this series of missions whose eleventh instance landed the first astronauts on the Moon.", "answer": "<b><u>Apollo</u></b> program (or Project <b><u>Apollo</u></b>)", "metadata": "Science - Other Science - Misc Science"}, {"question": "Use of this metric for placing students of color in EMR-type classes was largely barred in California by the case <em>Larry P v. Riles</em>. Stephen Jay Gould denounced attempts to singularly measure this metric in <em>The Mismeasure of Man</em>. Generations tend to perform better on tests evaluating this metric over time according to the Flynn effect. Robert Yerkes was hired to develop a method for the Army to take this metric in recruits. For the point, name this metric that can be measured on the Stanford-Binet scale, a \"quotient\" for which rates 90 to 109 as the average person's capability.", "answer": "<b><u>Intelligence</u></b> (or <b><u>Intelligence</u></b> Quotient; accept <b><u>IQ</u></b>)", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Psychology"}, {"question": "A Magonid royal with this epithet supposedly encountered a hairy tribe of savage men known as the <em>Gorillai</em>, who lend their name to the modern ape. That man with this nickname, Hanno, may have reached as far south as Gabon on a voyage that departed from Carthaginian territory in Iberia. Another man with this epithet funded the construction of a fleet of caravels, which led to the colonization of the Madeiras and the Azores. For the point, give this nickname held by a Prince of Portugal named Henry who encouraged 15th-century Portuguese exploration.", "answer": "The <b><u>Navigator</u></b> (accept Hanno the <b><u>Navigator</u></b>; accept Henry the <b><u>Navigator</u></b>; or Henrique, o <b><u>Navegador</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This philosophy\u2019s Three Obediences and Four Virtues prompted criticism from later scholars. A divine moral will was denied in \"The Discussion of Heaven\" chapter from a namesake book by this philosophy's scholar Xunzi. Emperor Shi Huangdi rejected this school of thought and adopted Legalism during the Qin [[CHIN]] Dynasty. Mencius argued that this philosophy regards human nature as \u2018intrinsically benevolent\u2019 in his explanation of the <em>Analects</em>. For the point, identify this ancient Chinese school of thought named for a sage of the Spring and Autumn period.", "answer": "<b><u>Confucian</u></b>ism (or <b><u>K\u01d2ng</u></b>ji\u00e0o; accept <b><u>Ru</u></b>ism; or <b><u>R\u00fa</u></b>ji\u0101; or <b><u>R\u00fa</u></b>ji\u00e0o; or <b><u>R\u00fa</u></b>xu\u00e9; accept answers indicating the philosophy of <b><u>Confucius</u></b> or Master <b><u>Kong</u></b>)", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {"question": "Chandragupta II erected pillars of this substance that tell of his conquest of the Vanga people and his crossing of the seven rivers of India. During the Yuan Dynasty, Wang Zhen published a pamphlet that outlined how waterwheels were used to operate furnaces, creating the pure form of this product. The Nok Culture of modern Nigeria was the first in Africa to make use of this metal. The Hittite Empire is often credited for smelting this metal to equip its armies. The Bronze Age preceded, for the point, an age named for what metal?", "answer": "<b><u>Iron</u></b> (accept <b><u>Fe</u></b>; or <b><u>Ferrum</u></b>; accept both Pig and Wrought <b><u>iron</u></b>; accept <b><u>Iron</u> </b>Pillar)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This battle was directly preceded by the death of General Jesse L. Reno at the Battle of South Mountain. The opening phase of this battle saw one side attempt to seize Dunker Church, and the carnage around a sunken road in this battle led to it being nicknamed \"Bloody Lane.\" Immediately followed by the issuance of the Emancipation Proclamation, for the point, what Maryland battle of the American Civil War was the bloodiest single day in U.S. history?", "answer": "Battle of <b><u>Antietam</u></b> (or Battle of <b><u>Sharpsburg</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This figure supposedly kept a blank cover copy of the novel <em>Dangerous Liaisons</em> so her ladies-in-waiting wouldn't gossip in the court. This royal demanded the dismissal of the Duc d'Aiguillon [[\"die\"-gee-YAWN]] after quarreling with chancellor Maupeou [[moe-POO]]. The Comtesse de la Motte's successful forgery of this woman's signature led to the Affair of the Diamond Necklace. This woman stated, \"Pardon me, sir, I did not do it on purpose\" after stepping on the executioner's foot shortly before being guillotined. For the point, name this wife of Louis XVI [[the Sixteenth]].", "answer": "<b><u>Marie Antoinette</u></b> (accept <b><u>Maria Antonia</u></b> Josepha Johanna)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "In this U.S. state, both Philip Kearny and Isaac Stevens were killed by Stonewall Jackson's troops at the Battle of Chantilly. A failed Union river crossing in this state was known as the \u201cMud March.\" A ship named after this state fought the USS <em>Monitor</em> in the Battle of Hampton Roads. Civilians had picnics to watch an early battle in this state fought at Manassas. The surrender at Appomattox Court House was in, for the point, which state that housed the Confederate capital in Richmond?", "answer": "Commonwealth of <b><u>Virginia</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Violet Bonham Carter wrote a biography of this man titled [this man] <em>As I Knew Him</em>. The Malakand campaign in India inspired this man to write his only fiction novel, <em>Savrola</em>. This man recounted his escape from a Boer POW camp in <em>London to Ladysmith via Pretoria</em>. Caesar's invasion of the British Isles begins this writer's <em>A History of the English-Speaking</em> <em>People</em>. For the point, name this winner of the Nobel Prize in Literature, who wrote <em>The Second</em> <em>World War</em> from his perspective as Prime Minister of the U.K.", "answer": "Winston <b><u>Churchill</u></b> (or Sir Winston Leonard Spencer <b><u>Churchill</u></b>)", "metadata": "Literature - British Literature - Misc Literature"}, {"question": "During this man's administration, blackmarketers named <em>vory y zakone</em> operated as semi-legal criminal syndicates in his nation. After many of his party members voted negatively of his leadership at the 17th Central Committee, this leader pointed an unloaded Mosin-Nagant rifle at the crowd. During the so-called \"Period of Yezhov,\" this leader conducted show trials of men like Mikhail Bukharin and other purported \"Trotskyites.\" For the point, name this dictator of the USSR who ordered the signing of the Molotov-Ribbentrop Pact with Nazi Germany.", "answer": "Joseph <b><u>Stalin</u></b> (or Joseph Vissarionovich <b><u>Stalin</u></b>; accept Iosif Vissarionovich <b><u>Stalin</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}], "bonuses": []}